<div xmlns:xsi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema-instance" xsi:schemaLocation="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml ../../schema/fhir-xhtml.xsd" xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">


    <div>
        <a name="scope"></a>
        <h2>Scope and Usage</h2>
        <h3>Motivations for a clinical profile registry</h3>
        <p>Data science thrives when practitioners have open access to data resources and information. In translational
            science, this ideally spans basic science “omics” data to and including clinical data. However, clinical
            data by its nature is sensitive and confidential, and can rarely be made freely available outside clinical
            record systems and controlled research repositories. However, data about clinical data, such as statistical
            summaries, frequencies, distributions, and relative counts does not contain any personal health information,
            and when presented about aggregated persons cannot be re-identified. Such summaries comprise the core of
            clinical profiles.
        </p>
        <p>The vision for a clinical profile registry is to include clinical profiles for diseases and phenotypically
            similar cohorts that are machine readable and consisting of aggregated statistics and facts about disease
            behavior derived from patient records. For example, a Fanconi anemia profile would include summary
            information about serum hemoglobin levels (e.g., mean, standard deviation, median value, and decile
            cut-points of the distribution) among other clinical variables and covariates across a group of patients
            with this condition. It is also attractive to consider demographic subsets of a clinical profile e.g.,
            summary information about clinical profile measures by race, sex, and age groups. Correspondingly, for
            chronic and common conditions such as hypertension, profiles about cohorts of treated persons may be
            separate from untreated persons. For conditions such as asthma, characteristics of persons in an acute
            exacerbation would differ materially from those presently asymptomatic.
        </p>

    </div>

    <!-- (recommended):
    <div>
    <h2>Boundaries and Relationships</h2>
    <p>
    Explains how this resource relates to others. Particularly important is to differentiate between appropriate usages
    for related resources when an implementer might be confused about what to reference when.
    </p>
    </div>
    -->

    <div>
        <h2>Background and Context</h2>
        <h3>Clinical profile data model requirements</h3>
        <p>As an initial step to defining the model requirements for a clinical profile, we identify core data
            (demographics, medications, common lab values, and coded information such as co-morbidities and procedures),
            some condition-specific measures (e.g pulmonary function tests for patients for asthma) that are readily
            available in electronic health records (EHR). The transition from patient-level data into a clinical profile
            would require reducing those data into to appropriate summary measures. For example, a comorbidity may be
            rendered in a clinical profile as the fraction of persons in a population expressing that comorbidity.
            Additionally, clinical profiles might express a degree of correlation between variables when they are
            significant, such as hemoglobin and hematocrit.
        </p>
        <p>To make such profiles useful to data scientists, they must be machine readable and conform to a published
            model. The present Clinical Profile FHIR Resource definition poses an initial model for containing profiles
            and relevant metadata. Each profile can be called with a FHIR API, and subsequently parsed using standard
            FHIR renditions such as JSON, XML, and RDF. The model defines the elements, boundaries, and relationships
            among the parsable data.
        </p>
    </div>


</div>
